弗里曼: 科学家们已经花费了40年寻找
Freeman: Scientists have been hunting it for 40 years,
解开宇宙奥秘的钥匙.
the key that will unlock the secrets of the universe.
如今他们已经发现了.
And now they've found it.
希格斯玻色子真的能告诉我们
Can the Higgs boson really tell us
一切是如何诞生的？
how all creation came into being？
我们的存在是否应归于
Do we owe our existence to
一些难以捉摸而又强大的东西？
something so elusive yet so powerful？
是否存在上帝粒子？
Is there a God particle？
空间、时间、生命本身,
Space,time,life itself.
宇宙的奥秘尽在穿越虫洞.
The secrets of the cosmos lie through the wormhole.
== 翻译： Allegro1756 ==
== 时间轴、校对： elderman ==
是否存在上帝粒子？
Is There a God Particle？
我们如何存在于宇宙之中呢？
How did we get to be here in this universe？
科学家们称宇宙诞生于一场纯粹能量的爆炸,
Scientists say our universe began as a burst of pure energy,
以某种方式,能量转变为物质,
but somehow,that energy transformed itself into matter
最终形成了恒星、行星,
which eventually became stars,planets,
以及所有组成你和我的元素.
and the stuff that makes up you and me.
我们的宇宙
Instead of being
没有变成瞬时的飞掠过的火球,
a fleeting fireball gone in an instant,
而是胶着了数万亿年.
our universe has stuck around for billions of years.
物理学家们很久之前就怀疑
Physicists have long suspected there must be
一定存在某些看不见的力场散布于整个宇宙,
some invisible force field spread across the universe
这种神秘的力量将能量变为实体物质.
mysteriously turning energy into solid matter.
现在,科学家们最终证明了
Now scientists have at last proven
理论中的这种力场是真实存在的.
that this theoretical force field is real.
他们从这个力场中获得了
They have produced from it
一个亚原子粒子--希格斯玻色子,
a subatomic particle known as the Higgs boson,
就是所谓的上帝粒子.
the so-called God particle.
上帝粒子能够解释我们存在的原因么？
Can it explain the mystery of our creation？
你见过玩陀螺吗？
Have you ever watched a spinning top？
还是孩子的时候,我记得自己
As a kid,I remember being mesmerized
喜欢看画着多种图案的陀螺旋转,
watching the painted shapes spinning on mine.
那些图案变得朦胧模糊,
The pattern became a ghostly blur.
似乎我可以把手指穿过这些图案,
Looked like I could stick my finger right through it.
可一旦转动停止,图案又变成原来那样清晰.
But once it stopped moving,the pattern became solid again.
物质的纯粹属性长久以来困惑着物理学家.
The solid nature of matter has long puzzled physicists.
过去四十年里,
Over the last four decades,
他们一直在考虑物质的存在是否
they have wondered if matter is solid
是由于被称作上帝粒子的
because of the Higgs boson,
希格斯玻色子造成的.
the so-called God particle.
你知道人们到底想把它称作什么,
You know what they really wanted to call it,right？
人们想称之为上帝[哔--]粒子....
They wanted to call it the God [bleep] particle...
这可能不能在电视台上播.
You probably can't put that on TV though.
...为了寻找它,我们花费了大量的
...given the amount of time and money we've spent
时间和金钱,
looking for this thing.
可我们都没能发现.
And we've missed it.
“哦[哔--]该死,这个粒子到底在哪儿？”
"Oh [bleep] damn. Where is that particle？"
Dan Hooper和Patrick Fox是理论物理学家,
Dan Hooper and Patrick Fox are theoretical physicists
就职于费米国家加速器实验室,
at the Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory
就在芝加哥城外.
just outside of Chicago.
和上千名物理学家一样,他们在职业生涯中
Like thousands of physicists,they have spent their careers
等待着希格斯玻色子会在
waiting for the Higgs boson to reveal itself
高速粒子对撞实验中现形.
in high-speed particle-collision experiments.
我们已经寻找了很久了,
It's something we've been looking for for a long time.
如果没有上帝粒子,
The universe would be very different
宇宙会变得与预想大不相同.
if it weren't for the God particle.
实际上,物理学家们认为有那么短暂的一瞬间,
Physicists believe,in fact,that there was a brief moment
宇宙中并不存在上帝粒子.
when the universe lived without the God particle.
在时间出现的时候,
It was at the beginning of time itself,
这比出现物理学家和这个游乐场还要早.
long before there were physicists and arcades.
把这个漂浮曲棍球桌想象成宇宙,
Imagine this air hockey table is the entire universe.
在它诞生时的大爆炸中,
When it was born in the big bang,
物理学家们认为这个时候
physicists think there were only
只有纯能量无质量的粒子.
massless particles of pure energy.
那么这时你能看到的是
So,what you can see here is that
所有的粒子以相同的速度运动,
all the particles are moving around at the same speed,
用这个速度就是光速.
at the speed of light.
它们在整个宇宙中基本没有质量.
They're all essentially massless in the whole universe.
但是宇宙并没有以这种状态持续很久,
But the universe did not remain that way for very long.
就在几分之一秒后,
After only a fraction of a second,
有些东西变了.
something changed.
就像有人扳了控制杆,
Almost like someone pulled a lever
使许多粒子慢慢停下来.
that made many of the particles grind to a halt.
某一点时,希格斯场打开了,
At some point,the Higgs field turned on,
这就使得一些粒子获得了质量,
and that made some of the particles acquire a mass,
同时意味着它们不再以光速运动.
which meant they stopped traveling at the speed of light.
光子,以黄色表示的,
The photons,the yellow ones,
继续以光速运动,
are zipping around at the speed of light,
而红色和绿色的表示得到了质量,
whereas the red and the green have acquired a mass
由于希格斯机制而导致
thanks to the Higgs mechanism
运动速度变缓.
and travel more slowly.
物理学家们认为刚刚在大爆炸之后,
Physicists believe that right after the Big Bang,
宇宙在冷却的过程中,希格斯场开始发挥作用了.
the universe began to cool,and the Higgs field turned on.
一些粒子开始和希格斯场相互作用
Some particles began to interact with the field
来获得质量.
and acquired mass.
另一些粒子则保持了无质量的纯能量状态.
Other particles remained massless bundles of energy.
几十年里,
In the decades for which
科学家们一直在撞碎粒子
scientists have been smashing together particles
来探究亚原子世界,
to probe the subatomic world,
他们已经发现了两种基本类型的粒子.
they have found two basic types of particles.
一种是费米子,
There are fermions,
一组携带有质量的粒子,
a group of massive particles that carry matter,
和玻色子,
and there are bosons,
携带能量的无质量粒子.
massless particles that carry force.
没有希格斯场的存在,
Without the existence of the Higgs,
所有的粒子都会是无质量的.
all particles would be massless.
那么如果没有希格斯场,
So,if there was no Higgs field,
你会有一些其他的力的载体.
you would have had these other force carriers.
它们也是无质量的,
They would have been massless,
因此,就像光子,
and therefore,like the particles of light,
它们都会以光速运动,
they would move at the speed of light.
没有这些质量,就绝对不可能出现
And without these masses,you can never have
各种原子或化学等之类的我们在宇宙中发现的
atoms or chemistry or any of the interesting stuff
有趣的东西,
we find in our universe.
组成你和我的物质也不会
The things that you and I are made up of
结合到一起
wouldn't be able to clump and coalesce
并减速.
and slow down.
没有任何结构,也就没有生命. 是的.
No structure,no life. Right.
一切都会很无聊. 对.
Boredom. Yep.
多亏了希格斯场,
Thanks to the Higgs,
我们的宇宙才能以现在的形式存在足够久,
our universe hung around long enough
以形成像人类这样的具有复杂结构的生命形式.
for complex structures likes human life to form.
但是为什么创造物质的希格斯场会启动呢？
But why did the matter-creating Higgs field turn on？
包括Dan和Patrick在内的许多科学家
Many scientists,including Dan and Patrick,
认为是大爆炸纯粹的暴力
think the sheer violence of the Big Bang
造成了希格斯场的运作.
jostled the field into action.
那么到现在,我一直在
So,up until now,I've been
用我的手控制希格斯机制的开或关.
turning the Higgs mechanism on and off by hand.
但是当然,在早期的宇宙,
But of course,in the early universe,
并不是以这种方式进行的.
it didn't happen that way.
就像水在你冷冻它的时候
And just like water freezes all on its own
自己就会结冰,
when you cool it,
希格斯机制也会在宇宙冷却时
the Higgs mechanism will turn on all by itself
自动启动.
as the universe cools.
这根台球杆假设代表了
So,this pool cue is supposed to represent
希格斯机制自身的不稳定.
how unstable the Higgs mechanism was all by itself.
就像你看到的这样...
And as you can see...
就这样. ...倒下去了.
Voilà. ...It just falls over.
科学家认为希格斯场,
Scientists think the Higgs field,
即是使能量转变成
the force that turned a ball of energy
我们物质宇宙的力,
into our physical universe,
完全是自动启动的.
turned on all by itself.
但也有一些人说这并不是偶然的,
But some will say that it was no accident,
必定有某位造物主将其启动.
and it must have been turned on by a creator.
而若要知道一切创始之谜
That mystery of creation may be answered
就需要更进一步的了解希格斯场.
if we learn more about the Higgs field.
科学家致力于扰动希格斯场
Scientists have been trying to disturb the field enough
来产生一个希格斯玻色子以便研究.
to make it produce a Higgs boson so they can study it.
这样物理学家制造了
It's an effort that has made physicists construct
科学史上最大的仪器,
the most powerful machine in the history of science,
大型强子对撞机,简称LHC.
the Large Hadron Collider,or the LHC.
过去四十年中,Lyn Evans负责建造
Lyn Evans has been responsible for building
位于瑞士日内瓦的CERN(欧洲核子研究组织)中的
every particle accelerator at CERN in Geneva
每台粒子加速器.
for the past four decades.
他创造的每台机器至今仍在工作.
All the machines he created are still working.
事实上,它们分阶段的共同工作.
In fact,they all work together in stages.
每一个老旧的机器现在负责
Each older one is now responsible for
给予粒子一个增加的推力,
giving the particles an incremental push,
赋予其越来越多的能量,
packing them with more and more energy,
最终将其注入巨大的、
and eventually feeding them into the giant,
17英里(27.36公里)长的环形LHC中.
17-mile-long ring that is the LHC.
Evans: 我1969年的时候来到CERN,
Evans: I came to CERN in 1969.
我的第一个工作就是研究
My first job was working on what is called
双等离子体离子源,
the dual plasmatron ion source,
也就是质子的来源.
which is actually the source of the protons.
然后就把它们加速.
And then,they are accelerated.
从线性加速器,
From the linear accelerator,
到助推器中获得更高的能量,
they go into a booster to get higher energy
接着进入超质子同步加速器,
and then into the super proton synchrotron,
就是我70年代开始工作的地方,
which I worked on in the '70s,
最后进入大型强子对撞机.
and finally into the Large Hadron Collider.
弗里曼：正是由于过去几十年中
Freeman: As particle accelerators
先进的粒子加速器,
have advanced over the past few decades,
他们能够让粒子
they have been able to get particles
获得越来越多的能量,
to higher and higher energies,
这就可以让他们
allowing them to create
在每次碰撞中创造
more and more massive new particles
更多种类的新粒子.
with each collision.
更为老旧的加速器只有足够的能量
The older accelerators only had enough energy
来使两个质子撞击形成一个新粒子...
to smash together two protons and make a new particle...
Aah! Aah!
...而这个粒子仅是质量加倍而已.
...with just double the mass.
但是理论家预测希格斯粒子的重量
But theorists predict the Higgs weighs
至少是一个质子的100倍.
at least 100 times as much as a proton.
物理学法则认定
The laws of physics say that
如果你给质子额外的动能,
if you give protons extra kinetic energy,
你能使它们撞击形成一个新粒子,
you can smash them together to form a new particle
其重量要比它们所有部分的总和高出许多倍.
that weighs many times more than the sum of their parts.
Evans：这就又回到了
Evans: Well,it all goes back to
最著名的科学方程式,
the most famous equation in science,
e=mc平方.
e=mc squared.
在LHC中,我们把能量转变成质量,
In the LHC,we are converting energy into mass,
如果你想制作出更重的东西,
and if you want to make very heavy objects,
你就需要非常多的能量.
you need a high energy.
弗里曼：把粒子物理学家想象成高尔夫运动员,
Freeman: Think of particle physicists as golfers
只是把击打的质子变成高尔夫球.
hitting protons instead of golf balls.
多年之后,他们就会变成越来越好的俱乐部(球队).
Over the years,they have gotten better and better clubs.
Evans：打个比方,我认为这根高尔夫球杆,
Evans: To make an analogy,I think this pitching wedge,
你可以想象是那些60年代的加速器,
you can think of as the machines of the '60s.
我能用它将球击出大概120码远,
This will take me about roughly 120 yards,
就像这样,
something like that,
因为它不能提供足够的击打能量...
because it doesn't have enough energy...
将球打出很远.
to go very far.
接下来这根就是质子-反质子对撞机,
Then,the next one was the proton-antiproton collider.
质子-反质子对撞机非常强大,
The proton-antiproton collider was much more powerful,
对,有点像七号铁杆.
and,yeah,a bit like a seven iron.
这次,粒子就可以获得更多的能量...
This time,the particles will get more energy...
...飞出更远的距离.
...and will go quite a bit further.
最后,当然,现在我们得到的--
And finally,of course,now we've got --
最后我们使用的是这台仪器,
at last,we've got the machine
可以产生出希格斯玻色子.
that can produce the Higgs boson.
如果你想打个比方,
And if you want an analogy with that,
这是我忠实可靠的球棒,
this is my faithful driver.
来吧.
So,here we go.
的确打得很远.
And that really moves it.
弗里曼：制造出像希格斯玻色子一样重的粒子
Freeman: Making a particle as heavy as the Higgs
需要比之前加速器产生的
requires far more energy
更多的能量.
than any previous accelerator has ever produced.
Lyn和CERN的庞大工程师团队
Lyn and the enormous team of engineers at CERN
已经把这项技术推进到极限.
have had to push their technology to the limits.
Evans：每次加速粒子,
Evans: Every time the particles come around,
它们获得一点点推动,
they get a little kick,
逐步提升他们的能量
increasing their energy incrementally
直到能量充满.
until we get up to the full energy reality.
弗里曼：物理学家最终得到了他们想要的能量.
Freeman: Physicists finally have the power they need.
但是捕获和研究希格斯玻色子
But capturing and studying the Higgs boson
需要的不仅仅是粗暴的力量.
is about more than brute force.
这就像在干草堆中寻针--
It's a quest to pull a needle from a haystack --
一个由亿万个亚原子粒子构成的干草堆.
a haystack made of trillions of subatomic particles.
对于大多数宗教信仰者来说,
For most religious believers,
神不能够被看到或者听到,
God cannot be seen or heard.
但是他或她存在的迹象就在我们周围.
But signs of his or her presence are felt all around us.
希格斯玻色子很难发现,
The Higgs boson is almost as elusive,
这也就是为什么追踪它变得很有挑战性.
which is why the chase for it has been so challenging.
希格斯玻色子可以在十亿分之一
The Higgs can pop in and out of existence
或一万亿分之一秒内出现并消失,
in one billionth of a trillionth of a second
只留下细微的证据
and only leaves behind the faintest of evidence
证明它存在过.
that it was ever there.
那么科学家如何去寻找
So,how do scientists find something
永远不可见的东西呢？
that can never be seen？
当物理学家Joe Incandela还是个孩子的时候,
When physicist Joe Incandela was a kid,
他的父母希望他能成为一名玻璃雕塑家.
his mom and dad hoped he would become a glass sculptor.
Incandela: 我小时候对艺术非常感兴趣,
Incandela: I was very much interested in art as a kid.
我父母也强烈鼓励我.
My parents encouraged that very strongly.
他们也曾对艺术很感兴趣.
They'd been very interested in art.
我发现我最喜欢的一位吹玻璃者
And I discovered one of my favorite glassblowers
是名化学家,
was a chemist,
这算是我去大学学习化学
and so,that kind of gave me an excuse
的一个理由吧.
to go to college and study chemistry.
然后我学习化学的时候,还需要学习物理,
And so,when I took chemistry,I had to take physics.
这又恰好符合我的兴趣,
And that just immediately hit me.
这真的很神奇,
This was really fascinating.
这才是我想要学习的东西.
This was the stuff I wanted to study.
弗里曼：Joe现在是LHC的
Freeman: Joe is now the leader of
两个主要项目的其中之一的领导者,
one of the two major experiments at the LHC.
他引导着世界上千名物理学家,
He directs thousands of physicists from around the world
他们都有着同样的疑问,
who are all on the same quest
希望能够发现我们知道的一切
to figure out how and why
是如何和为什么会存在.
we and everything we know exist.
Incandela: 我们真的努力去理解
Incandela: We're really trying to understand
我们在宇宙中的位置.
our place in the universe,you know？
一切都是由什么构成,
What is everything made of,
而它们又如何成为这样,
and how did it become what it is？
这类基本问题.
These sort of fundamental questions.
弗里曼：Joe认为LHC可以解答这些问题.
Freeman: Joe believes the LHC will answer these questions.
在LHC中的碰撞重建了刚刚大爆炸之后
The collisions at the LHC recreate the energy conditions
发生的能量状况.
that happened just after the Big Bang.
科学家试图对希格斯场启动
Scientists are trying to gain some insight
并扩散到整个宇宙的时候
into the moment when the Higgs field turned on
获得更多的了解,
and spread across the entire universe,
希格斯场创造了物质、恒星、
creating matter,the stars,
最后创造了我们.
and eventually us.
希格斯场的力的载体是希格斯玻色子,
The force of the Higgs field is carried by the Higgs boson,
而玻色子的产生只能通过
and a boson can only be detected by creating
创造场中的一个能量扰动.
an energy disturbance in the field.
Incandela:制造出希格斯玻色子
Incandela: Turns out the Higgs is actually
就在某种程度上决定了整个宇宙
determining the whole universe in some way,
所处的状态,
what state it's in,
还有这些粒子存在的表现形式.
and how these particles will manifest themselves.
那么如果我们使用像LHC这样的加速器,
So,if we take an accelerator like the LHC,
并提供足够的能量,
and we provide enough energy,
然后将质子撞在一起,
and we smash the protons together,
你就能够从杂乱的背景中
we can actually pull,if you like,
找出希格斯玻色子
a Higgs particle out of this fabric
并对其进行研究.
and study it.
弗里曼：正如这些
Freeman: Just like these glass balls
充满很多东西的玻璃球,
are filled with a bunch of stuff,
在LHC中碰撞的质子中
the protons that are smashed together at the LHC
也充斥着很多东西--
are also filled with stuff --
比如夸克和胶子.
particles called quarks and gluons.
当质子碰撞时,
When protons collide,
上千个新粒子从中迸出.
thousands of new particles come shooting out.
研究碰撞余波是个辛苦的工作,
Studying the aftermath is a painstaking job,
就像从一大堆碎玻璃中筛出我们需要的.
like sifting through piles of shattered glass.
Incandela: 我们在找的是特定的模式,
Incandela: We're looking for certain patterns.
能量、粒子和碎片残骸以多种方式
The energy,the particles,the debris
散布到检测器周围,
is scattered around the detector in various ways,
对于一个希格斯玻色子,你就需要非常特定的模式,
and for a Higgs,you have very specific patterns
这就依赖于它的衰退.
depending on the decay that's involved.
弗里曼：但是上帝粒子赐予物理学家的是曲折,
Freeman: But the God particle has blessed physicists with a twist.
在能够辨认出它之前就已经消失了.
It always vanishes before it can be spotted.
希格斯玻色子的衰退几乎是即时的,
The Higgs decays almost instantly.
它的寿命极短,我们无法检测.
Its lifetime is so short,we can't measure it.
这样我们就检测了它的衰退产物.
And so,we detect it by its decay products.
弗里曼：为了检测希格斯玻色子,像Joe这样的物理学家
Freeman: To detect a Higgs,physicists like Joe
需要检查质子碰撞后的余波
have to look at the aftermath of proton collisions
来找出它存在的证据.
to figure out what the original particles were.
如果Joe能够分析
If Joe could analyze
这场玻璃球碰撞后的每一片残骸,
each piece of debris in this glass collision
并计算出它们的抛射轨道,
and calculate its trajectory,
他就能基于
he could reconstruct the crash
这些残留的部分重建碰撞.
based on the remnants that came out of it.
Incandela: 我们看到的大多数的相互作用,
Incandela: Most of the interactions that we see,
都是直接产生了我们能够识别
they immediately create a pattern
但又不感兴趣的模式,
that we recognize as not interesting,
我们就能将它们排除.
and we can reject them.
迄今,我们已经排除了
So,we reject,by far,
碰撞的大部分痕迹.
the vast majority of the collisions.
弗里曼：值得研究的产物唯有那些
Freeman: The only collisions worth studying are when
质子完美对齐下的撞击.
the components of the protons are perfectly aligned.
如果一个质子中的一个夸克同另一个质子中的
If a quark inside one proton makes a head-on impact
一个夸克迎头撞击,
with a quark inside the other,
这样几乎所有的碰撞能量
then almost all the energy of the collision
集中于一个地方.
is concentrated in one place.
这样就足够产生一个希格斯场的波动,
This creates a strong enough ripple in the Higgs field
来产生一个希格斯玻色子.
to make a Higgs boson.
但这样的撞击几乎从没发生过.
But this type of collision almost never happens.
现在这些罕见事件,好吧--真的很罕见.
Now,those are rare events,okay -- really rare.
那么大体来说,
So,roughly speaking,
产生一个希格斯玻色子的概率是一万亿分之一.
a Higgs production is almost one in a trillion.
弗里曼：自从LHC启动以来,
Freeman: Since the LHC has been running,
已经进行了大约1000万亿次撞击.
it has produced about 1,000 trillion collisions.
Incandela: 如果你有1000万亿个沙粒,
Incandela: If you had 1,000 trillion grains of sand,
你就能用它们填满一个奥林匹克规模的游泳池.
you would fill an olympic-sized swimming pool.
[ Zip! Crunch! ]
弗里曼: 但是只有几百个撞击
Freeman: But only a few hundred of those collisions
可能会产生希格斯玻色子.
might produce a Higgs.
Ugh.
几百粒沙子
A few hundred grains of sand
仅能盖住你的指尖.
would just cover the tip of your finger.
这看起来像是不可能的任务,
It is a seemingly impossible task,
但是震惊世界的是,
but to the world's astonishment,
Joe和上千名物理学家
Joe and thousands of other physicists
推翻了这种不可能.
pulled off the unfathomable.
涉及其中的仅是非常少的痕迹,
There's very few events involved,
我们能够追踪它从哪里来.
and we can trace where this comes from.
弗里曼：2012年七月四日,
Freeman: On July 4,2012,
Joe有幸能宣布
Joe had the honor of announcing
在LHC工作的团队向前迈了一大步.
that the teams at the LHC had made a giant step forward.
他们检测到了一个新粒子,
They had detected a new particle
重量在125到126兆电子伏,
that weighed between 125 and 126 giga-electron volts,
符合对希格斯玻色子重量的预测.
the predicted range of the mass of the Higgs.
...因为这些结果现在由全球
...because these results are now global
和全人类所共享,
and shared by all of mankind.
所以,非常感谢你们所有人.
So,I thank you for that.
[鼓掌]
[ Applause ]
我的职业生涯中从没见过这样的情况,
I've never seen anything like it in my career.
大家非常兴奋,人们都很高兴.
There was a lot of excitement. People were very happy.
Fox：很难相信,这像是人们去看
Fox: It was just incredible,like going to
甲壳虫乐队什么的--每个人都很疯狂,
see the Beatles or something -- everybody was crazy,
在物理研讨会中
and there was spontaneous applause
人们都会自发的鼓掌,
at a physics seminar,
这种情况从未发生过,你知道吗,
which never happens,you know？
这就像是等了几十年之后
It's like seeing the Beatles
才能看到甲壳虫乐队的音乐会一样.
after waiting for it for decades.
对,是的.正是.
Right,right. Exactly.
Evans：我希望这不是结束,
Evans: It's,I hope,not the end,
这只是漫漫长路的一小步,
but it is a little step in a long journey.
我们花了40年才走到这一步,
It's taken us 40 years to get here.
不过我们现在向着我们对自然的了解
And we now have a marvelous step forward
走了了不起的一步.
in our understanding of nature.
Incandela:希格斯场和我们
Incandela: The Higgs field is unlike
之前见过的都不一样.
anything we've ever seen before.
希格斯场是我们无论去哪都要
The Higgs field is part of this fabric
与之相互作用的结构的一部分.
that we're interacting with everywhere we go.
从这个角度,某种程度上我们
From it,we can,to some extent,
甚至可能去了解宇宙的进化.
even possibly understand the evolution of the universe.
这是个意义深远的发现.
It's a very profound finding.
弗里曼：这次发现被称为继爱因斯坦写下
Freeman: It's being called the greatest scientific discovery
质能方程后的最大的科学发现.
since Einstein wrote "e=mc squared."
Incandela: 一个伟大的艺术品正是那些,
Incandela: A great piece of art is something that,
可以永远存留的.
you know,lasts forever.
一个新的科学发现或发展
A new scientific discovery or development
对人类进步的贡献是永久的.
is something that contributes to humanity for all time.
弗里曼：这个粒子可以解释
Freeman: The particle that could solve the riddle of our existence
我们的存在之谜.
has been spotted.
那么我们接近了了解宇宙的最后一步么？
Are we closing in on a final understanding of the universe？
Dan Hooper认为答案可能会更加复杂,
Dan Hooper thinks the answer may be more complicated,
可能并不只有一种希格斯玻色子,
that there may not be one Higgs boson
而是有五种.
but five.
弗里曼：人们认为希格斯玻色子可以解释
Freeman: The Higgs boson is supposed to explain
宇宙中所有物质的来源.
where all the matter in the universe came from.
但在过去十年中,我们得知
But in the last decade,we've learned that
宇宙中大部分是由
most of our universe is made up of
称作暗物质的看不见的粒子组成.
invisible particles called dark matter.
实际上暗物质比普通物质
In fact,there is five times more dark matter
多出了5倍.
than ordinary matter.
现有理论预测希格斯玻色子的存在
The current theory that predicts the existence of the Higgs boson
无法解释这些奇特物质的存在.
offers no explanation for this strange substance.
那希格斯玻色子具有隐藏的阴暗面么？
Could the Higgs have a hidden dark side？
理论物理学家Dan Hooper
Theoretical physicist Dan Hooper
用去了他整个职业生涯在等待
has been waiting his whole career
希格斯玻色子
for the announcement that
的发现.
the Higgs boson has been discovered.
Hooper：我一直在我的电脑上
Hooper: I was up streaming it on my laptop,
热切地等待结果.
enthusiastically waiting for the results.
你等待某些东西如此之久,
You wait for something this long,
当你等到的时候,
and when it happens,
不论你认为自己准备的多么充分,
no matter how prepared you think you should be for it to happen,
都仍会感到离奇,
it seems surreal.
仍会觉得意外,
It seems unexpected
不论之前如何的期待结果.
no matter how expected it should have been.
弗里曼：希格斯玻色子被发现了.
Freeman: The Higgs has been found.
但是一个大谜团仍然存在,
But a huge mystery still remains.
暗物质是什么？
What is dark matter？
Hooper：宇宙学的一个最大问题,
Hooper: One of the biggest problems in cosmology
就是当我们用望远镜观看远方,
is that when we look in telescopes at space,
我们发现只能看到物质总量中
we find that only a small fraction of the total matter
由像原子和其他已知物质组成的一小部分.
is made up of things like atoms and other known material.
其中的大部分都是一类幻影物质,
Most of it is some sort of elusive material
由于缺乏一个更好的名字,我们称之为暗物质.
that,for lack of a better name,we just call dark matter.
弗里曼：半个世纪以来,对亚原子世界的探索
Freeman: Half a century of exploring the subatomic world
揭示了一个组织结构,
has revealed an organizing structure
被称作“粒子物理标准模型”.
called the standard model of particle physics.
科学家发现了物质的12种基本粒子,
Scientists have discovered 12 fundamental particles of matter,
费米子,均分在夸克和轻子中.
the fermions,equally split among quarks and leptons.
有四种粒子传播力,
There are four particles that transmit force
比如电和磁.
like electricity and magnetism.
这些都是玻色子.
These are the bosons.
接下来完成这幅图的是
And then,completing the picture,
一个非常奇特的玻色子,希格斯玻色子.
is one very special boson,the Higgs boson.
但是标准模型并没有解释暗物质.
But the standard model has no explanation for dark matter.
另外还有一个严重的缺陷,
And it has another serious flaw.
粒子物理标准模型
One of the biggest problems with
其中一个最大的问题
the standard model of particle physics
就是所谓的“级列问题”.
is something we call the hierarchy problem.
我们知道希格斯玻色子
We know that the Higgs boson
质量大约有126兆电子伏
has a mass of about 126 giga-electron volts
或简称gev.
or gev.
这是一个非常重的粒子,但是我们天真地
This is a heavy particle,but naively,
根据标准模型预想
we'd expect,according to the standard model,
希格斯玻色子会比这个还要重很多.
that the Higgs should be much,much heavier than this.
但由于某种原因,它的质量很小.
And for some reason,it's lighter.
弗里曼：希格斯玻色子有着重量问题.
Freeman: The Higgs has weight issues.
比如希格斯玻色子会把质量分给其他粒子,
Just as the Higgs boson gives mass to other particles,
而其他的粒子会轮流
other particles,in turn,
给希格斯玻色子质量.
contribute to the mass of the Higgs.
当物理学家计算希格斯玻色子可以
When physicists work out how big the Higgs should get
从其他粒子那里获得多少质量,他们的结果表明其重量
from these other particles,they come up with a weight
会比其本身重数十亿倍.
billions of times heavier than it is.
科学家们只能敷衍这个数学问题
Scientists have had to fudge the math
来创立标准模型.
to make the standard model work,
虽然他们知道有些东西错过了.
fully knowing something is off.
Hooper：为了解释这个问题,
Hooper: So,to explain this,
有些东西需要非常精确的互相抵消,
something has to very precisely cancel one another
使希格斯玻色子的质量恢复到观测值.
to restore the Higgs mass to its observed value.
[演奏蓝调音乐]
[ Blues music plays ]
弗里曼：当希格斯玻色子和暗物质给Dan施加了太大压力时,
Freeman: When the Higgs and dark matter weigh too heavily on Dan,
他就抽身于物理放松精神.
he takes a mental break from physics.
研究暗物质的他和他的叫做Congregation的乐队,
The only dark matter he and his band,the Congregation,
演唱的则是受伤的心.
sing about are broken hearts.
而Dan却发现音乐规则
But Dan can't help but find parallels
和宇宙的规则有相通之处.
between the rules of music and the rules of the universe.
[音乐结束]
[ Song ends ]
很有趣的是许多我知道的物理学家
It's amazing how many physicists I know
也都是老练的音乐家,
who are also accomplished musicians,
也许这之间是有关联的.
and maybe there's reasons for that.
你在粒子物理中发现的规律
The patterns that you find in particle physics
常常和音乐理论中的规律
are oftentimes pretty similar to
有着非常相似的对称性.
the kind of symmetries you can find in music theory.
[演奏蓝调音乐]
[ Blues music plays ]
弗里曼:Dan认为自然界中存在某种规律
Freeman: Dan believes there is a pattern in nature
可以解释希格斯玻色子较小的质量
that can solve the small mass of the Higgs
以及暗物质.
and explain dark matter.
这正是一种对标准模型的修饰,
It is an idea that modifies the standard model.
称作“超对称”(费米子与玻色子之间的对称性).
It's called supersymmetry.
♪ ...looking for so long
♪ but each time that I've tried ♪
Hooper:对于每块物质,
Hooper: For every piece of matter,
每种费米粒子来说,
every kind of fermionic particle,
都要有一个玻色子粒子
there has to be a bosonic particle,
作为力的载体.
a force carrier.
光子需要光微子,
So,the photon requires a photino,
电子需要Selectron【找不到翻译呢...】.
the electron a selectron.
在音乐理论中,
In music theory,
如果你弹奏大调音阶,比如C大调音阶...
if you have a major scale like this "C" major scale...
[演奏音阶]
[ Scale plays ]
...而同样的音符通过不同的排序演奏
...those same notes have to make up an "A" minor scale
就是A小调音阶.
if you just play them in a different order.
[演奏音阶]
[ Scale plays ]
那么在一个超对称世界中,
So,in a supersymmetric world,
你不能只有光子而没有光微子,
you can't have a photon without a photino,
而在音乐理论中,
and in our music theory,
不能只有大调音阶而没有小调音阶.
you can't have a major scale without a minor scale.
弗里曼：根据超对称原理,
Freeman: According to supersymmetry,
我们观测到的粒子
the particles we have observed in nature
仅仅是整个图景中的一半.
are only half of the picture.
一定互相存在大量的超对称粒子.
There must be massive superpartners for each one.
这些超对称粒子中的一种可能就是暗物质.
One of these superpartners might even be dark matter.
那么在大多数超对称理论中,
So,in most supersymmetric theories,
最轻的新粒子会是
the lightest of the new particles you introduce
暗物质的最佳候选者.
is a very nice candidate for dark matter.
在早期宇宙,还是非常热的时候,
So,in the early universe,when the universe was very hot,
这些粒子的数量极为丰富,
these particles would have been produced in copious numbers.
但大多数都会被毁掉,只有一点点会存留下来,
Most of it would get destroyed,but a little bit would survive,
留下来的一点点可能形成了
and that little bit could make up
今日宇宙中的暗物质.
all of the dark matter in our universe today.
弗里曼：根据Dan的理论,如果对称是
Freeman: According to Dan,if symmetries
我们宇宙的基本部分,
are a fundamental part of our universe,
他们就能够找到希格斯玻色子真正的质量.
they can set the Higgs at the correct mass.
Hooper：如果超对称的确存在,
Hooper: If supersymmetry exists in nature,
那么每次得到一个粒子,
then every contribution given
比如说一个电子,
from a particle,like an electron,
就会又得到一个与之相反的
gets an opposite contribution
超对称粒子Selectron,
from its superpartner,the selectron,
这样它们是平衡的.
and they balance.
它们在大部分地方都互相抵消,
They cancel each other out for the most part,
留给我的是非常轻的希格斯玻色子.
leaving us with a pretty light Higgs boson.
弗里曼：超对称解释了
Freeman: Supersymmetry makes sense
标准模型无法解释的现象.
where the standard model does not.
这就可以解释小质量的希格斯玻色子
It can explain the small mass of the Higgs
以及什么是暗物质.
and what dark matter is.
这是这里有个陷阱,
But there is a catch.
为了使超对称理论为真,
In order for supersymmetry to be true,
就还需要不仅一种希格斯玻色子,
there has to be not just one Higgs
而是5种.
but five.
如果自然界真的具有超对称性质,
If nature really is supersymmetric
而且只有一种希格斯玻色子,
and there were only one Higgs boson,
这个理论就会存在
the theory would contain
我们称为“反常”的数学问题.
mathematical problems we call anomalies.
就会存在许多悖论.
It would contain paradoxes.
为了解决这些问题,就需要引入额外的希格斯玻色子.
And to solve this,you need to introduce extra Higgs bosons.
如果CERN能够发现第二个或第三个
If CERN were to discover a second or third
甚至第四个第五个希格斯玻色子,
or fourth or fifth Higgs boson,
就可以有力的增加超对称的例子,
it would strengthen the case for supersymmetry,
甚至我们不需要亲眼
even if we hadn't observed
观测到这些超对称粒子本身.
those superparticle partners themselves yet.
如果要解释
If we are to explain the universe
我们已知的宇宙,
as we already know it,
去了解暗物质如何会伴随着一般物质,
to understand how dark matter lives alongside ordinary matter,
科学家还要再发现五种希格斯玻色子.
scientists need to find evidence for five Higgs bosons.
花了40年才发现一个上帝粒子,
It took 40 years to find one God particle.
我们注定会错过终极真理吗？
Is the ultimate truth destined to elude us？
希格斯玻色子担负着
The Higgs boson is responsible for
解释全宇宙物质来源的重任.
giving everything in the entire universe mass.
这对于一个亚原子粒子来说 是一个很重大的工作.
That's a big job for one subatomic particle.
一些科学家认为这对于一个粒子来说过于重大了.
Some scientists believe it's too big a job for one particle.
如果上帝粒子本身
What if the God particle
并不会自身携带重量呢？
isn't carrying the weight all by itself？
或许宇宙的真正设计
Perhaps the real design of the universe
需要多于一种希格斯玻色子扮演上帝.
needs more than one Higgs to play God.
John Ellis是CERN的一个理论物理学家,
John Ellis is a theoretical physicist at CERN.
他一直在花时间出主意,
He spends his time thinking up ideas,
很多主意在实验中常被证明错误.
ideas that experiments here often prove wrong.
但这对于John来说还好.
But that's okay by John.
Ellis: 那么我的工作就是
Ellis: So,no,my job is to
为实验要寻找的对象提供想法,
think of things for the experiments to look for,
然后,就像我常说的,
and then,as I like to say,
我希望他们能发现一些不同的东西.
I hope they find something different.
弗里曼：Albert de Roeck是位实验物理学家,
Freeman: Albert de Roeck is an experimental physicist.
他则花时间检验主意,
He spends his time testing ideas,
希望能够证明它们是错误的.
hoping to prove them wrong.
我加入这些实验希望能够找到
I joined these experiments in pursuit of
打破标准模型的东西,
finding something to crack the standard model,
通过找到超出标准模型之外的东西
possibly kill the standard model
将其扼杀掉.
by finding things beyond the standard model.
弗里曼：Albert,实验者,
Freeman: Albert,the experimentalist,
John,思考者,
and John,the thinker,
自从开始就同时都成为了
have both been part of the hunt for the Higgs
寻找希格斯玻色子的组成部分,
since the beginning.
希格斯玻色子起初设想用来解决一个谜题--
The Higgs boson was originally supposed to solve one mystery --
“w”和“z”玻色子的质量,【w、z玻色子：弱相互作用的承载粒子】
the mass of the "w" and "z" bosons,
它们都非常之重.
which are extremely heavy.
另两种玻色子基本没有质量.
The other two bosons are massless.
物理学家认为“w”和“z”玻色子非常的重
Physicists proposed the "w" and "z" get heavy
是因为它们都单独与
because they alone interact with
无处不在的看不见的力场--
an invisible field that is everywhere --
希格斯场相互作用.
the Higgs field.
但是其他的玻色子不这样.
But the other bosons do not.
随后,当标准模型写出后,
Later,when the standard model was written,
希格斯场的概念就被延伸到
the idea of the Higgs field was extended
一个更为重大的工作上--
to take on a much bigger job --
赋予整个宇宙质量.
to give mass to the entire universe.
这是一类附加的东西,
It was sort of added on.
并不是这种机制发明的原因.
It was not why this mechanism was invented.
弗里曼：但是像Albert和John这类的物理学家知道
Freeman: But physicists like Albert and John know
这个粒子可能并不能担负起
this one particle may not be responsible
赋予所有物质质量的重任.
for giving mass to everything.
Ellis: 物理学中有大量的理论
Ellis: There's myriads of theories out there in physics
都超出了标准模型,
beyond the standard model,
这些理论具有的普遍特点是
and it's a general feature of them
它们预测的东西比
that they predict something more complicated
单独的希格斯玻色子复杂得多.
than just a single Higgs boson.
弗里曼:John和Albert一直在尝试
Freeman: John and Albert have been trying to
基于标准模型并同时修复其错误
come up with new theories,building upon the standard model
来想出一些新理论.
while fixing what is wrong with it.
这意味着他们必须改变他们对
It means they must change their predictions
希格斯玻色子到底是什么的预测.
for what the Higgs actually is.
已经预测出了几种不同的
Several varieties of Higgs particles
希格斯玻色子.
have been predicted.
你可以想象是冰淇淋的不同口味.
You can think of it like flavors of ice cream.
如果LHC发现的是纯的、过时的香草口味希格斯玻色子,
If the LHC found a plain,old,vanilla Higgs,
这就确认了物理学家已经知道的东西.
it confirms what physicists already know.
[唉]
[ Sighs ]
但是如果发现的是有更多让人兴奋的口味
But if it turns out to be a more exciting flavor
比如薄荷巧克力块口味,
like mint-chocolate-chip,
这就为物理打开了新的令人兴奋的可能.
it opens up new thrilling possibilities for physics.
[拥抱亲吻]
[ Smooching ]
哦！
Oh!
其中一个可能就是
One of these possibilities would be that
有两种希格斯玻色子,分别担任不同的工作.
there are two Higgs bosons,each with a different job.
已经有了非常多的想法认为
So,there's been,you know,a number of ideas that say,
“好吧,可能会发生一些外包的情况,”
"well,maybe there's a bit of outsourcing going on,"
一个希格斯玻色子
and that there is one Higgs boson
负责“w”和“zed”玻色子,
for the "w" and the "zed"
另一个则负责物质粒子.
and another one for the matter particles.
弗里曼：可以想象John是“z”玻色子,力的载体,
Freeman: Imagine John is a "z" boson,a force carrier.
Albert是个夸克,物质的载体.
Albert is a quark,a matter carrier.
John是个总所周知的咖啡狂,
John is a well-known coffee addict.
Akbert是人们所知的巧克力狂,
Albert is a well-known chocoholic.
那么把这个咖啡馆当做一个希格斯场,
Say this café is one Higgs field
巧克力店则是另一个.
and this chocolate shop is another.
当John经过咖啡馆,他会放慢脚步获得质量.
When John passes the café,he will slow down and gain mass.
De Roeck: 但另一个粒子,我自己,
De Roeck: But the other particle,myself,
会快速经过咖啡馆,
would just zap through until
直到我遇到了能与我作用的场,
I encounter the field with which I'm interacting,
这就会给我质量--
and that would give me mass --
在这个例子中就是巧克力商店.
in this case,a chocolate shop.
弗里曼：标准模型
Freeman: The standard model
并不包括两种希格斯场,
doesn't include two Higgs fields,
这也是这种想法能够吸引John和Albert的原因.
which is why this idea is so appealing to John and Albert.
如果我们发现不仅有一种希格斯玻色子,（或说不仅有一种希格斯场）
If we were to find that there is more than one Higgs,
这就意味着物理学
that would mean for sure
肯定超出了标准模型.
there is physics beyond the standard model.
Ellis: 现在如果我们寻找的
Ellis: Now,if what we're looking at
是并不十分精确的东西,
is something which is not exactly,
比如你祖母的希格斯玻色子,
you know,your grandmother's Higgs boson,
某种方式来说确实让人很兴奋.
that could actually,in a way,be even more exciting.
弗里曼: 现在,当新发现的希格斯玻色子
Freeman: So far,there are some signs of anomalies
开始衰退时,表现出了反常的迹象,
in the way this new particle decays,
表明会有其他种类的希格斯玻色子
suggesting an exotic flavor of the Higgs
隐藏在数据之中.
might be lurking in the data.
还仍有大量的数据等待分析.
And there are still piles of data waiting to be analyzed.
De Roeck: 我真心希望这个希格斯玻色子
De Roeck: I actually hope that this Higgs boson
是通往超出标准模型的
is gonna be a portal to the new physics
新的物理学的大门.
which we're going to find beyond the standard model.
这非常让人兴奋,
And that would be exciting because
因为每次这种事情的发生,我们就能够学到新东西.
each time that happens,we learn something new.
弗里曼：LHC也暗示了
Freeman: The LHC may be hinting that
希格斯玻色子只是众多扮演者中的一个,
the Higgs is only one of many players.
它不会全然就是上帝粒子.
It may not be the God particle after all.
这个人认为创造宇宙的真相
This man thinks the truth about the creation of the universe
比长久以来才发现的希格斯玻色子还要深远,
lies deeper than the long-sought Higgs,
我们只是才刚开始想象
that we owe our existence to
希格斯玻色子是我们存在的原因.
particles we have only just begun to imagine.
希腊哲学家德谟克利特,
It was the Greek philosopher Democritus
第一个提出了原子.
who first thought of the atom.
他认为原子是
He imagined it to be
物质形成的最小单位,
the smallest possible building block of matter,
它不能再分了.
one that could never be divided.
他的想法成功延续了2000年,
His idea was good enough to last 2,000 years,
直到核子时代的到来才揭示了更深层次的真相.
until the nuclear age came along and revealed a deeper truth.
原子也是由更小的东西组成,
The atom is made up of smaller things.
比如夸克和电子组成了原子,
Just as particles like quarks and electrons make up the atom,
它们是更小的,更基本的组成单位,
smaller,more fundamental building blocks
而又可能由希格斯玻色子组成.
might make up the Higgs boson.
如果我们发现它们,就不仅能揭示
If we can find them,they could reveal
物质如何存在的,包括物质为什么存在.
not just how matter exists but why it came to be.
Francesco Sannino是位理论物理学家
Francesco Sannino is a theoretical physicist
就职于欧登赛的南丹麦大学.
at the University of Southern Denmark in Odense.
他居住于能够让他的想象力狂野驰骋的完美城镇.
He lives in the perfect town to let his imagination run wild.
欧登赛是著名儿童故事作家
Odense is the birthplace
汉斯·克里斯蒂安·安徒生
of the famous children's story author
的出生地.
Hans Christian Andersen.
我们就在安徒生居住地的附近,
So,we are in the Hans Christian Andersen neighborhood.
他在这里出生,
He was born here,
他描绘了很多这样的街道,
and he has drawn a lot from these streets.
就像你看到的,
As you can see,
这就像是故事书中的一页.
it looks like taken by a page from a storybook.
弗里曼：但不同于这个童话般的小镇,
Freeman: But unlike this fairy-tale town,
我们对于
our understanding
宇宙的基本组成单位的了解
of the fundamental building blocks of the universe
并不是完美无缺的.
is not picture-perfect.
标准模型
The standard model
认为希格斯玻色子是基本粒子,
regards the Higgs boson as a fundamental particle,
但是Francesco的想象力驱使他看得更远,
but Francesco's imagination is driving him to look further,
看他能否看到希格斯玻色子的内部.
to see if he can peer inside the Higgs.
Sannino: 根据标准模型,
Sannino: According to the standard model,
希格斯玻色子是一种基本粒子,
the Higgs is a fundamental particle.
这表明它不会被再分.
It means it's not made of something else.
那么看这面墙,是白的.
So,look at this wall. It's white.
但实际上是有三种不同的光
But the truth is that there are three different lights
组合在一起显现出白色.
combined together making this white.
那么如果我把我手
In fact,see what happen
放在墙面前会发生什么.
if I put my hand in front of the wall.
我可以把它分解为三种不同的颜色,
I can resolve there's three different colors,
绿、蓝、红,
the green,the blue,and the red.
它们共同形成了白光.
Together,they form the white light.
弗里曼：就像白光
Freeman: Just as a white light
实际上由三种不同颜色的光组成,
is actually made up of three different colors,
Francesco在想希格斯玻色子
Francesco wondered if the Higgs
是否由不同种类的粒子组成.
is made up of several different particles.
这就说明了希格斯玻色子
This would mean the Higgs
并不是所有物质存在的根基.
is not a fundamental root of all matter.
他和许多同事认为
He and many of his colleagues think
希格斯玻色子自身就被一种新的自然力控制,
the Higgs itself is governed by a new force of nature,
他们称这种力为人工色(力).
something they call the technicolor force.
Sannino: 如果你要深入到希格斯玻色子内部,
Sannino: If you look deep inside the Higgs,
你会发现它由其他东西组成.
you will find it's made of something else.
[钢琴演奏古典音乐] 【应该是肖邦圆舞曲】
[ Piano plays classical music ]
弗里曼：Francesco认为
Freeman: Francesco believes
希格斯玻色子用新节奏在跳舞.
the Higgs boson dances to a new tempo.
把这些乐高玩具块当做普通夸克,
Imagine these Lego bricks are ordinary quarks
这块板就是胶子代表的力（强核力）
and this board is the force of the gluons
可以将它们组合在一起.
that holds them together.
为了制作一个质子,我们要三个夸克.
To make a proton,we need three quarks.
根据人工色原理,
According to the technicolor theory,
希格斯玻色子都是一样的,
the Higgs is just the same,
但是由不同种类的夸克组成--
but it is made up of different types of quarks --
techniquarks【这个怎么翻译呢...】.
techniquarks.
Sannino: techniquarks由一种新的力
Sannino: The techniquarks are held together
组合在一起,就是人工色(力).
by a new force,a techniforce.
它们相互作用产生的能量
And the energy that comes from the interactions
自发的为希格斯粒子提供质量.
also automatically provides the mass of the Higgs.
弗里曼：物理学家知道
Freeman: Physicists know
普通夸克的不同排列,
ordinary quarks in different arrangements
创造了不同粒子.
make different particles.
一种排列是质子,
One arrangement is a proton.
另一种排列就是中子.
Another arrangement is a neutron.
Techniquarks的工作方式也相同,
Techniquarks work the same way.
一种方式排列,你就得到了希格斯玻色子,
Arrange them one way,and you get a Higgs.
另将techniquarks用另一种方式排列,
But arrange those techniquarks another way,
你就会得到一些别的
and you get something else
科学家正在寻找的东西,
scientists have been looking for,
暗物质粒子.
a dark-matter particle.
Sannino: 这真的很像乐高玩具,
Sannino: So,it's really like a Lego brick.
你把它们放在一起,
You put them together,
一种形式你得到了希格斯玻色子,
and in one form,you get the Higgs.
另一种形式你能得到暗物质.
And in another form,you can get the dark matter.
弗里曼：或许标准模型中希格斯玻色子
Freeman: Perhaps the reason the standard-model Higgs
不能解释暗物质的原因
can't explain dark matter
是因为希格斯玻色子是变相的暗物质,
is because the Higgs is dark matter in disguise
不同形式的粒子的结合则通过
and both particles are held together
人工色(力).
by the techniforce.
这将会是一种新的自然力,
There will be definitely a new force of nature,
这对于人类来说是一个奇妙的机遇
so it will be fantastic opportunity for mankind
来面对一个新的力.
to face a new force.
弗里曼：Techniquarks可以通过多种方式结合起来,
Freeman: Techniquarks could be glued together in many ways,
创造出几种新式粒子.
constructing several brand-new particles.
这些粒子还正等待LHC的发现,
Those particles could be waiting to be discovered at the LHC
不过这要等到2015年重新以更高能量启动后了.
when it comes back online at much higher energies in 2015.
Francesco希望最近发现的希格斯玻色子
Francesco hopes that the Higgs boson recently discovered
是第一候选者.
is the first candidate.
我们总会一无所知,
We just won't know it
直到我们有足够的力量将其撞开.
until we have enough power to crack it open.
Sannino: 我觉得这是人类的责任
Sannino: I think it's the duty of human beings
来了解什么在我身边以及什么造就了我们.
to understand what is around us and what makes us.
我认为这的确是一个很神奇的机遇
I think this is really a fantastic opportunity
来把科学的边界推到如此程度.
to push the boundaries of science to that degree.
弗里曼: 那么所谓的上帝粒子
Freeman: Does the so-called God particle
真的有多个方面吗？
have multiple faces？
或许希格斯玻色子并没有我们认为的那么万能.
Perhaps the Higgs is not as almighty as we thought.
我们还有更多的离奇古怪的想法,
But there are much more mind-bending ideas.
或许让我们存在的东西
What makes us exist
可能完全就不存在.
could be objects that don't really exist at all.
当我们仰望夜空,
When we look up at the night sky,
月亮凝视着我们,
our moon peers down at us.
它似乎神奇的悬挂在稀薄的空气中,
It seem to be magically suspended in thin air,
即使我们知道它是由重力
even though we know it's being held in place
保持在天空中的.
by the force of gravity.
那如果宇宙中所有的物质
What if all matter in the universe
都被一些别的东西锚定在那里呢,
is actually being anchored by something else,
一些比重力更陌生
something far stranger than gravity
比上帝粒子更奇异的东西？
and far stranger than the God particle？
哈佛大学的Howard Georgi的
Howard Georgi from Harvard University
大半生都是一名粒子物理学家.
has been a particle physicist for most of his life.
但是最近,他的事业发生了转变,
But recently,he has made a career change.
他现在是一位非粒子物理学家.
He is now an unparticle physicist.
我一直试图思考
I was trying to think about
在LHC中得到的结果其实是很不同寻常的,
what the LHC might see that was really unusual,
我想到是否LHC中
and it occurred to me that whether there was something
表现出来的完全不是粒子.
that might show up at the LHC that was not particles at all.
这就是我作为非粒子物理学家
That was the beginning of my career
为事业的开端.
as an unparticle physicist.
弗里曼：就像很多物理学家一样,
Freeman: Like many physicists,
Howard一直在修正标准模型,
Howard has been trying to fix the standard model
并创立一些新理论.
and come up with new theories.
当他正在计算他的等式时,
While working on his equations,
他注意到了一些让人茫然的计算.
he noticed some puzzling calculations.
物理学中,像光子这样无质量的粒子
In physics,massless particles like photons
在数学中以负整数表现.
show up in math as negative whole numbers.
Howard从他的等式中得到的负数,
Howard's equations were giving him negative numbers,
但是它们不是整数.
but they weren't whole numbers.
它们只是负分数.
They were negative fractions.
Georgi: 你这样分析,
Georgi: You do this analysis,
就会得到2又1/2的无质量粒子,
and you might get 2 1/2 massless particles.
然后,你抓着头说,
And then,you scratch your head and say,
“什么？发生了什么？”
"What？ What is going on？"
弗里曼: Howard知道这些一半的分数
Freeman: Howard knew these half numbers
并不代表半个粒子.
weren't half particles.
它们是一些新的东西,他称之为非粒子.
They were something new. He called them unparticles.
Georgi: 有些事正在发生,
Georgi: There's something happening.
是一些物理学上的事,
There's some physics,
但又不是我们现在所用的物理学.
but it's not the sort of physics that we're used to.
弗里曼：Howard进行了更深入的数学计算,
Freeman: Howard probed the math deeper
更多的了解非粒子.
and learned more about unparticles.
他意识到出现分数的原因
He realized the reason they came out as fractions
可能是由于分形维数,
is because they have fractal dimensions,
就像是一棵树的分枝.
much like the branches of a tree.
Georgi: 如果你看一棵树,
Georgi: If you look at the tree,
它不是只有一个维数,
it's not one-dimensional,
因为它长出了很多树枝,
because the tree comes and it branches,
然后这些树枝再分枝.
and then the branches branch again.
这样分枝之后再分枝,
And the branch's branches branch again.
接着再分枝后再分枝,等等.
And the branch's branch's branches,et cetera and so on.
一个真正分形中,这会永远进行下去.
In a true fractal,that would go on forever.
弗里曼：非粒子就像这棵树的分枝.
Freeman: Unparticles are like the branches of this tree.
这些图形模式都是相同的,
The pattern is the same
无论你离得多么近或者多么远来看.
no matter how close or how far away you look.
但是一般粒子就像树叶,
But normal particles are like the leaves on the tree.
离得越近看它,它就越大.
The closer you get,the bigger they look.
Georgi: 我喜欢这种把树叶当做
Georgi: I like the idea of thinking of the leaves
标准模型中的东西的想法,
as the objects of the standard model
因为它们都有确定的大小,
because they have a definite size,
正如一个粒子所具有的质量,
like a mass that a particle has,
而树的分枝却没有确定的大小.
whereas the branches of the tree don't have a definite size.
弗里曼: 构成宇宙的所有的粒子
Freeman: All of the particles that make up our universe
都有质量,
have mass,
由于希格斯玻色子,物理学家相信质量的存在.
which physicists believe exists because of the Higgs.
但如果希格斯玻色子内部的粒子
But perhaps those particles in the Higgs
实际上受限于看不见的非粒子世界,
are really being governed by an invisible world of unparticles
挑战已知的物理学法则.
that defy the laws of known physics.
这意味着宇宙中所有的物质粒子
It would mean all matter particles in the universe
都像是这棵树上的树叶.
are like the leaves on this tree.
而一个无形的非粒子树干则是它们的根基,
An invisible tree of unparticles may be their anchor,
隐秘地支撑起整个宇宙.
the secret underpinning of the entire cosmos.
Georgi: 这正是非粒子物理的观点.
Georgi: That's really the point of unparticle physics.
为了让这棵无形的树变得有趣,
In order for this invisible tree to be interesting,
就需要让它在某种程度上
it has to somehow interact
与标准模型中的粒子相互作用.
with the particles of the standard model.
树叶需要以某种方式长在树干上,
The leaves will have to somehow be held up by that tree
树干上也需要有树叶.
or vice versa.
弗里曼：至今,
Freeman: So far,
LHC的实验尚未表明非粒子的迹象,
there are no signs of unparticles at the LHC.
但Howard作为一个非粒子物理学家是不会放弃的.
But Howard isn't giving up as an unparticle physicist.
坦白地说我不认为我们得到的是正确的图景.
I don't think we've got the right picture frankly.
当你有些奇怪的东西,
When you have something that strange
与我们所知的都不一样,
and that different from what we know,
这就显得非常诱人.
it's tantalizing.
这样,我认为这是值得继续下去
And so,I think it's worth continuing
尝试解决掉这个复杂的数学计算,
to try to beat on this complicated mathematics
并看看能否取得更多进步.
and see if can make some more progress.
弗里曼：希格斯玻色子真的是上帝粒子吗？
Freeman: Is the Higgs boson really the God particle？
还是某些更深层次、
Or is there something else underneath,
更加神秘的东西？
something more mysterious？
我们存在的理由
Do we owe our existence
应该归于我们从未检测到的东西吗？
to something we might never detect？
就现在来说,科学家继续研究
For now,scientists continue to probe
他们成功发现的上帝粒子,
the God particle they have triumphantly discovered,
希望有一天他们能发现答案.
hoping they will one day find out.
希格斯玻色子和我们玩了几十年的
The Higgs boson has been playing a game of hide-and-seek
捉迷藏,
for decades.
现在我们终于发现了它,
Now that we have finally found it,
或是类似于它的东西,
or something like it,
我们的问题比答案更多.
we have more questions than answers.
物理学家每次找到一扇门的钥匙,
Each time physicists find the key to one door,
他们打开门却发现还有另一扇紧锁的门,
they open it just to find,another door.
然后现在,又有五扇门.
And then,five more.
也许希格斯玻色子的确是上帝粒子.
Maybe the Higgs boson really is,God's particle.
一个宇宙谜题的解答,却正是另一个谜题.
A cosmic puzzle whose solution,is just another puzzle.
宇宙留给我们的,注定都是谜题.
Destined to remain,an enigma.
== 翻译： Allegro1756 ==
== 时间轴、校对： elderman ==